Guide to the Howard Goddard Papers ALBA.126
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Howard Goddard Papers
1937-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Goddard, Howard, 1911-1997
ALBA.126
0.75 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 folder in an oversize shared box
Howard Goddard (1911-1997) dedicated much of his life to working as a union activist, from organizing in the early 1930s to a lifelong career with the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (IUMMSW). Goddard joined the International Brigades to fight against Franco in Spain in 1937 and returned in 1938 with the rank of Captain. This collection contains ephemera from the Spanish Civil War and correspondence between Goddard and various veterans and veteran organizations.
Provenance
The Howard Goddard Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1997 by Esther Brown. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Howard Goddard (1911-1997) was born in Harrodsburg, Kentucky. The family moved to Southern California in 1921 and he took his first job when he turned 13. After graduating from high school he worked in Trona, California for a chemical mining company. His experience organizing and fighting for union rights in this company town (which involves one of the first landmark cases successfully argued before the National Labor Relations Board) solidified his belief in the workers' cause and the international fight against fascism. Arriving in Spain in March 1937 via the Pyrenees, Goddard was assigned to a Spanish-speaking company in the International Brigades. After recovering from wounds at Belchite and helping to plan the Battle of Ebro, Goddard was promoted to captain of his company in October of 1938. Goddard returned from Spain in late 1938 and continued to work and organize unions from Denver to Los Angeles, representing the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers for most of his career. He married and had two children. He was an active member of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and at the time of his death was living in San Francisco.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Subject Files. The bulk of this series contains ephemera associated with the Spanish Civil War, including certificates of honor and documents of affiliation with the Spanish Communist Party and the International Brigades. Other subject files include anniversary programs and newsletters from the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives, the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (both the New York and Bay Area posts), and the 60th Anniversary Tribute in Spain in 1996. Of note is a transcript of an oral history interview done by Art Day in 1986, addressing Goddard's involvement with the labor movement in the 1930s and 1940s.
Series II: Correspondence. Each folder in this series contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence between the recipient and Goddard. The recipient's name titles each folder. Many of the letters written in Spanish include Goddard's own translation. The bulk of the letters, mostly to and from veterans of the Spanish Civil War, is between Goddard and former veteran John V. Murra. Murra's correspondence also contains clippings and other items that he sent to Goddard. Notable are letters between Goddard and José Antonio Valledor Alvarez, a former commander of the 15th International Brigade.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged alphabetically by subject. Series II is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Subject Files, 1937-1996; Undated.
II, Correspondence, 1985-1996; Undated
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Howard Goddard Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Belchite (Spain); Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Printed ephemera.; Correspondence.; Articles.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Valledor Alvarez, José Antonio.; International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers; Goddard, Howard, 1911-1997; Murra, John V.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Subject Files
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives: 50th Anniversary Commemoration, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adolph Ross Project: A Biographical Dictionary of American Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-39 Questionnaire, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party: Promotional Pocket Calendar, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Goddard, Howard: Oral History Interview Conducted by Art Day, Sep 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores: Clippings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - International Brigades: Clippings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Brigades: 60th Anniversary Tribute in Spain, Nov 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Spain: Certificate of Naturalization, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Spain: Pension Acquisition for Veterans, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Spanish Civil War: Association of the Friends of the Soviet Union Identification Card (Albacete), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Spanish Civil War: Carnet de Honor, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Spanish Civil War: Citation of Honor, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Spanish Civil War: Communist Party of Spain Identification Card, Jan 1, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Spanish Civil War: Embarkation Card, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Spanish Civil War: General Orders of Promotion, Oct 1, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Civil War: International Brigades: Certificate of Service, Nov 10, 1938 (Box Tamiment Shared MSOS006)
  - Spanish Civil War: James Lardner Memorial Fund, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Civil War: Military Service Booklet, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Civil War: Order Form for Uniform, Sep 25, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civil War: Pesetas, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Civil War: Repatriation Papers, Nov 30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Civil War: Socorro Rojo Internacional Identification Card, Aug 10, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Spanish Civil War: Telephone Conference Call Records, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Spanish Civil War: Vaccination Certificate, Nov 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Spanish Civil War: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Identification Card, Jan 1, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Spanish Civil War: Wallet, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Veterans: Obituaries and Eulogies, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Anniversary Events, 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Newsletters, 1985-1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Bay Area Post: Anniversary Events, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Bay Area Post: Newsletters, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Doménech, Castillo Jesús, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Eladio, Paula, Feb 2, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Geiser, Carl, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Levenson, Leonard, Jan 27, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - MacLeod, Donald, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Marantz, Anton Peter, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Murra, John, 1985-1995 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Nelson, Steve, Nov 22, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Shelton, Denis, Oct. 11, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Valledor Alvarez, José Antonio, 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Watt, George, Jan 18, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 43)